Okay today's דף daf is נ"ט nun tet and we're going to
start at the very top but before we do we're still of
course in the middle of the issue about how do you measure
and I wanted to use a minute because I had a chance
over the weekend to look up an important point that we've been
discussing which relates to the תחומין tchumim of you know if you
just think about New York City so here's our picture of New
York City you got the Bronx there right but anyway if you
look at our picture of New York City I don't know New
York looks something like this right and this is New Jersey right
and this is New York City oops New York City right and
this is Queens or Brooklyn whatever this is the Bronx so the
question is how do you travel right from how do you travel
from like New York to Riverdale Manhattan to Riverdale which people do
right because even if you square it off right you get a
little piece of what is this Queens or Brooklyn
Brooklyn
and you get New Jersey but you know but you don't get
Riverdale up here and even if you square this part off right
you don't get it down so how do people you know how
do people do it and even if it's something like this which
I think it is even if it's something like that right so
you get maybe part of New York City but you don't get
all of New York City and people still would travel from lower
down so that's the question so the most obvious solution answer to
that is although stated nowhere in the גמרא Gemara is that if
the squares overlap since this is defined as the city the squaring
even before you do the two thousand so if the squares overlap
then it's like they're all one city right would that be the
הלכה halacha or not so there are a number of תשובות tchuvot
that actually here I'll just tip this a little bit so I
can see there's a number of תשובות tchuvot that actually talk about
the Brooklyn Bridge which is what here or like that the Brooklyn
Bridge and want to know if the story of the Brooklyn Bridge
is remember we talked about if there's a בית דירה beis dira
by the bridge is it all considered part of the תחום tchum
and they ask about whether that counts because you know although although
here it does seem from רש"י Rashi that as long as it's
basically a guy collecting tolls on the bridge it would count I
don't know for some reason they're not the the discussion is more
around some place in the middle of the bridge where somebody can
like live or a little booth anyway there's a couple of תשובות
tchuvot around the Brooklyn Bridge and whether you get the whole bridge
or not and if the בית דירה beis dira is not immediately
juxtaposed to the city if it's somewhere in the middle of the
bridge and to what degree does it have to be a physical
part of the bridge or just near the bridge anyway so there's
all these discussions around the Brooklyn Bridge a couple of תשובות tchuvot
about them and a number of them end in saying well bit
of the bridge or not can count when you look at a
map it all works out or something like that so what do
they mean when you look at a map it all works out
so presumably they mean this they mean that even that ultimately these
squares overlap and I actually looked and found that there is
a חזון איש Chazon Ish that says this that says on his
commentary in עירובין Eruvin
he
actually says
so if you take a look he actually says here on the
top of ט"ז tet zayin he says he says אם יש שבעים
אמה ושיריים עושה קרפף לשניים להיות כאחד im yesh shivim amos v'shiyayrim
oseh karpaf l'shnayim l'hiyot k'echad
which is what we've been discussing right that the what do you
call it that if they that the if there's 100 and like
140 feet between them they're considered one he says יש לעיין אם
יש עיבור הפגומים היוצאים דמוציא את המידה כנגדם ועושה אותו כמין טבלא
yesh l'ayein im yesh ibbur hapgumim hayotzim dimotzi es hamidah k'negdam v'ose
oso k'min tavla if you square it off ואוויר הזה שמתעבר עמה
פוגע בעיר אחרת v'avir hazeh shemitaber ima pogea b'ir acheres and the
squaring off you know you know injects itself meaning overlaps with another
city מהו שעיבור הזה יעשה שתיהן כעיר אחת mahu sheibbur hazeh yaaseh
shteihen k'ir achas
will the overlapping as when you square it off if it overlaps
with another city will it make it one city and then he
goes and he quotes from רש"י Rashi that
well no the reason we're putting these two is nothing to do
with politically that it's considered boroughs it's just that there's more than
140 feet from the edge of one to the edge of the
other so 140 feet normally is considered a gap to be one
city anyway and then he basically tries to argue based on a
רש"י Rashi that yes that if the squaring of it makes it
overlap with another city it's considered a city and I did find
one or two contemporary you know תשובה tshuva that basically take that
for granted so it's interesting it is not so much discussed but
actually the חזון איש Chazon Ish says that yes if squaring it
off makes it overlap with another city then it's all considered one
city and that explains and that tends seems to be the practice
in terms of עירוב תחומין eruv tchumim so that explains how come
nowadays you know how come people travel
Exactly.
Well, I don't know if I'd call נחל שחור, Nachal Shachor, that's
another question, but okay. Yes, so that is very, so I just
wanted to share that with you, that's an explicit חזון איש Chazon
Ish and although not discussed too much in the classic sort of
פוסקים poskim and תשובות, teshuvos, it is assumed in contemporary practice. Exactly.
What's the מצב matzav here? Exactly.
Does anybody disagree with the חזון איש Chazon Ish on this?
I have not found anybody that disagrees. Okay, so before you walked
in I was saying that there were some discussion about whether the
Brooklyn Bridge counts as an expansion of Brooklyn or not all around
the question of what's the בית דירה beis dirah connected to a
bridge and does it constitute, but a number of the תשובות teshuvos
end whether or not it's connected, if you look at a map
it's not a problem. Clearly. They clearly overlap. And presumably that reason
is because once you square it off, it all overlaps. All right,
so let's take a look. So that was just a little very
practical application of everything we've been discussing. So let's take a look
at the top now of נט עמוד א. Nun Tes Amud Aleph.
Now the משנה Mishnah said that if there are competing measurements, one
is, one is greater than the other, you go by the one
that's greater, because you're lenient when there's issues about עירובין. Eruvin. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, דף נט עמוד א, Daf Nun
Tes Amud Aleph, במקום שריבו הן במקום שמיעטו לו, B'makom she'ribu hein
b'makom she'miatu lo, you go only by the one that's greater, not
the one that's
lesser. אימא סיפא אף למקום שריבו, Eima seifa af l'makom she'ribu, you
even go by the one that's greater. Now what does that mean?
So רש"י Rashi says the question is, well, I mean, you know,
יש בכלל מאתיים מנה. Yesh bichlal masayim maneh. If you're going to
the one that's further out of the city, obviously you're also passing
the one that's closer to the city, so it's a pretty like
silly question with a silly answer. Yes, of course, we know we
mean you can go to the closer one and certainly go to
the further one. תוספות Tosafos says that's not the question. תוספות Tosafos
says the question is that you know we spent all of yesterday
discussing all these complicated ways to measure hills and valleys and so
on. So תוספות Tosafos says if here's your city and here you
have one marker at this location and down here of the same
side you know you're at the west but you have a marker
over here at this location. So תוספות Tosafos says the גמרא's Gemara
question is I understand you're allowed to go over here but when
you're going this way you should you should stop here, you shouldn't
ignore this one because maybe this is closer because you know maybe
the ground was more sloped here so therefore it's not straight as
the crow flies, right? If it's a small if it's if it's
like you know a shallow angle you actually do include the vertical
in it and maybe the ground was very flat here, so this
could be completely legitimate for this position because of the sloping and
the hills or whatever. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is you're right.
If you're right it means אף למקום שריבו Af l'makom she'ribu you
can go this far if you're here but if you're here you
have to stop where that marker is. A very different answer than
רש"י, Rashi, but the nice thing about it is that it plays
off of yesterday's discussion and says that it's not always as the
crow flies. It depends on the topography, so you have to respect
both markers that you find. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues, ריבו לאחד ומיעטו לאחד. Ribu l'echad u'miatu l'echad. If one was
long and the other was short, you go by the long one.
So that sounded exactly like the previous case in the משנה. Mishnah.
הא תו למה לי? Ha su lama li? Why do you need
this other case? היינו הך. Hainu hach. It's exactly what you said,
you have competing markers. So the גמרא Gemara says היינו הך. Hainu
hach. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. ריבו אחד
ומיעט אחד. Ribu echad u'miat echad. If it's not that they're competing
markers like you know you have one guy did the whole did
everything, did the surveying, but one was closer and one was shorter,
one of his markers like I described. No no, maybe two guys
did the surveying and one guy had a you know one guy's
marker came out further than the other and תוספות Tosafos says actually
to show the contrast with the previous one, if they're even on
the same exactly at the same on the same like you know
the same space. So one guy's marker was there and the other
guy's marker was here. So here you could say you know this
might actually be legitimate for this for this location for the what
is it the southwest side, whereas that's the appropriate one for the
northwest side.
But let's say in one location on the northwest side you have
two competing markers, maybe from two different people.
Okay, so it's a variation. It's from the way רש"י Rashi says
it's different people did it and תוספות Tosafos says they're actually literally
competing because they're about the same location.
It's interesting if you look at the גרסא girsa because here it
says in the גמרא Gemara the way they're quoting ריבו אחד מיעט
אחד Ribu echad miat echad which means one person versus the other,
whereas in the משנה Mishnah it says ריבו לאחד.
Ribu l'echad. I know, but I mean לאחד l'echad one of the
measurers presumably is how it's being read at least according to רש"י.
Rashi. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר אביי Amar Abaye הכי קאמר
Hachi ka'amar excuse me, so here's what it means. ריבו אחד ומיעט
אחד שומעין לזה שריבה. Ribu echad u'miat echad shomin l'zeh she'riba.
So if one had more and the other had less, you listen
to the one that had more. So again here the שומעין לזה,
shomin l'zeh, this one, seems that it's not one person came up
with different measurements but two different surveyors came up with different, like
you always... You know, you give the job to the guy with
the lower estimate, so here you give the job to the guy
with the higher estimate as it were, with the higher marker, even
if they're competing and even if it's literally on the same
topography. אמר אביי Amar Abaye now said אביי: Abaye: ובלבד שלא ירבה
יותר ממדת העיר
באלכסונה, u-vilvad shelo yarbeh yoter mi-midat ha-ir be-alakhsonah, that provided that his
measurement does not exceed the diagonal of the city. Meaning, if this
guy is like way off, right? If you would go out and
do the re-measure yourself and this guy was like way off, he
wasn't, not only was he not 2000 אמות, amot, it wasn't even
2800, right? Which is the diagonal, right? Because this way you get
2800. So if this guy is way off, then you don't include,
then you don't do it. Now of course the fun thing is,
if you're remeasuring, why are you going by any of this? Why
not go, you know, by the remeasuring? The גמרא Gemara imagines somehow
that these signposts are there and they, you know, are established, and
as long as there's some legitimacy to them you keep them. For
as long as the further one is within the diagonal 2800. Now
it still would be pretty funny that you would allow the diagonal
of 2800 even if it was perpendicular to the city. So from
תוספות Tosafot it sounds like, but then you don't know why it
mentions the diagonal. That we're actually talking that they are competing over
here, you know, and that they, so if they are competing over
here, you know, why mention the diagonal? It would be just the
same as saying that if they're competing over here, as long as
it's within the 2000 אמות. amot. So it's not clear from the
גמרא. Gemara. I would say a simpler read of the גמרא Gemara
is that they're not at the diagonal and we actually allow the
fact that there is some error and it's still legitimate as long
as it's not a gross error defined by more than 2800. But
תוספות Tosafot makes it sound like they are on the diagonal, yes.
This seems to be one of those examples where we can create
a הלכתית halakhic reality even though it may not be consistent with
the actual reality.
Right, that we go by the markers even though now, right, that's
what's funny because it sounds like now we're actually remeasuring and we're
still going to accept the markers, you know, even though now based
on our remeasuring we may, maybe we should realign everything. I know
it is, it is quite interesting about that.
But there are a few other cases where this happens.
Yeah, and here's again certainly because it's all rabbinic, which is the
end of the משנה. Mishna. So that's what the גמרא Gemara ends
with: לא אמרו חכמים את הדבר להחמיר אלא להקל. lo amru chakhamim
et ha-davar le-hachmir ela le-hakel. They didn't say this to be strict,
only to be lenient. So now that and the משנה Mishna is
explaining why you believe even a male and a female slave. Normally
slaves are not believed for issues of testimony. So the גמרא Gemara
says ותניא: ve-tanya: לא אמרו חכמים את הדבר להקל אלא להחמיר. lo
amru chakhamim et ha-davar le-hakel ela le-hachmir. They weren't being lenient, they
were being strict. אמר רבינא Amar Ravina said רבינא, Ravina, רבינא: Ravina:
לא להקל על דברי תורה אלא להחמיר על דברי תורה. lo le-hakel
al divrei Torah ela le-hachmir al divrei Torah. The whole institution of
תחומין techumim
was
not to be lenient against a biblical principle. How could you be
lenient against a biblical principle? So the whole institution of תחומין techumim
was a stringency, was to add something that the תורה Torah was
not demanding. תחומין דרבנן Techumim derabbanan
because תחומין techumim are themselves a rabbinic institution, but once they're a
rabbinic institution we are prepared to go leniently. And as we knew
like a month ago, there's a position in the גמרא Gemara that
we always go כדברי המיקל בעירוב. ke-divrei ha-meikel be-eruv. That's when it's
a הלכתית halakhic debate. Our משנה Mishna talks about when there's actually
this like debate of markers, which one to trust, but the end
of it says even a question about somebody testifying as to remembering,
like oh yes, you know I remember that the תחום techum of
the city used to be until here, and even trusting a female
and a male slave. So this leads תוספות Tosafot into an interesting
discussion about do you trust slaves? And תוספות Tosafot also throws into
the discussion women when it comes to issues that are biblical because
the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it is because this is
rabbinic, that's not only why you, you know, go by the further
marker rather than the nearer marker, but the משנה Mishna really emphasizing
that it's all rabbinic seems to be emphasizing why we trust and
why we believe the slaves. So תוספות Tosafot says so would that
mean if it's biblical you would not? What about the fact and
as I mentioned, if you look at the first line of
תוספות: Tosafot: תחומין דרבנן, techumim derabbanan, תוספות Tosafot says משמע mashma it
sounds like אי הוי דאורייתא לא מהימני. i havei de-oraita lo mehumni.
If it was biblical they wouldn't be believed, slaves and תוספות Tosafot
assumes not just slaves, but it's anybody that would not normally serve
as an עד, ed, as a formal witness and תוספות Tosafot assumes
that women and children are included. Now you could say the משנה
Mishna maybe specifically means slaves because you know you know the assumption
was there, not saying it's a reality, but the assumption was that
slaves weren't trustworthy. But anyway let's see what תוספות's Tosafot answer is.
ואף על גב דמעשה בכל יום שמאמינים נשים, ve-af al gav de-ma'aseh
be-khol yom she-ma'aminim nashim, even though every single day we trust women
בשחיטה ובניקור, bi-shechitah u-venikkur, basically we go home our wives feed us
meat, so they're basically saying this meat which we knew was once
a living breathing cow, right, was shechted properly and the חלב chelev
was removed, וליטרום חלה u-li-terum challah and חלה challah was taken from
the bread. היינו משום דהוה בידו קודם שנעשית השחיטה הוה בידו לשחוט.
hainu mishum de-havah be-yado kodem she-na'asis ha-shechitah havah be-yado lishchot. That's
because there's this principle of בידה. beyada. And the way the אחרונים
achronim sort of explain it, something that had a חזקת איסור, chezkat
issur, like you knew that this cow at one stage of its
life was אסור, assur, was אבר מן החי, ever min hachay, it
wasn't yet שחט'ד, shechted, so there you only, you can believe somebody
only if it's like בידה, beyada, only if in theory they could
make it kosher. Now, does she know how to לשחוט? lishchot? Well,
so they could find somebody to do it, but they in theory
are in a position to control it. Something that was, what, women
can be שוחטות? shochtet? Yes, women can be שוחטות, shochtet, הכל שוחטין.
hakol shochtin. Yes, but, but right, but that's, but still it's theoretical,
meaning even if she, you know, this particular woman couldn't have been
שוחטת. shochethet. But anyway, no, she just doesn't know how.
She particularly, not about women.
This particular woman. If she knew how, then she could. Yes. No,
no, but so they're saying you, we can believe, you can believe
her even if she doesn't know how because in theory she could
שחט'ר, shechter, in theory she could bring it to the שוחט shochet
and get it שחט'ד. shechted. Women are believe, yes, women can be
שוחט, shochet, that is true, yes, that's like the first משנה mishnah
in חולין Chullin says that. Okay, so yes. But they don't. I
know. Anyway, well, alright, alright, anyway, so this is an important principle
of
עד אחד נאמן באיסורין. ed echad ne'eman be'issurin. Of עד אחד נאמן
באיסורין, ed echad ne'eman be'issurin, we believe even a single person and
it's not a formal עדות, edut, so women are believed as well.
By the way, there's an interesting תשובה teshuvah in Rav Moshe about
a woman being a משגיח mashgiach where he says it's
allowed. Anyway, so, and, so anyway, that's the principle of עד אחד
נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman be'issurin which does not have the formal
rules of עדות edut and there is some time where it's important
that it be in theory you be able to control it, בידה,
beyada, when it's, when it was a חזקת איסור. chezkat issur. Okay,
עירובין eruvin is a little bit different because עירובין eruvin you can't
control where the תחום techum is. It either is or isn't in
this place, you're not in a position to have made it so.
Anyway, so this leads to a discussion in תוספות Tosafot about when
are people that normally don't fall in the formal category of עדות,
edut, when are they trusted. Often they're trusted in biblical issues of
עד אחד נאמן באיסורין, ed echad ne'eman be'issurin, but maybe only when
it's בידה beyada or so on and maybe there are times where
they're only trusted because it's rabbinic. So here the גמרא gemara emphasizes
that it's because it's rabbinic. And תוספות Tosafot sort of lump the
slave... I know I didn't read the rest of the discussion. The
rest of the discussion is not so pleasant. I know, Rivka, I
know what the rest of the discussion is, I summarized it. The
rest of the discussion is he says maybe we only trust women
for בדיקת חמץ, bedikat chametz, גמרא gemara says because it's rabbinic. Well
why is it, is it not בידה? beyada? תוספות Tosafot says, well,
maybe you can't trust them because it takes so much effort and
maybe they're lazy. Yes, I know. Okay, anyway, yes. I did know
what the end of the תוספות Tosafot said, Rivka. Yes, I know.
They could have mentioned the discussions in גיטין Gittin about who is
able to testify for like the death of a husband.
Right, so this is not the same. עדות אשה edut isha is
not the same. Anyway, by תחומין techumin there is a, there is
conflicting evidence whether תחומין techumin needs actual עדות edut or whether it's
under the category of עד אחד נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman be'issurin
and does not need formal עדות. edut. This גמרא gemara certainly, you
know, doesn't quote עד אחד נאמן באיסורין ed echad ne'eman be'issurin but
says because it's rabbinic we are lenient. Yes, and it is true
that the rest of that תוספות Tosafot gives more conflict, you know,
a less pleasant discussion about, about תוספות's Tosafot analysis of why sometimes,
you know, it assumes that women would be trusted and sometimes it
seems that it would not, were it not for the fact that
it was rabbinic. Okay, let's look now at the next משנה. mishnah.
עיר שיחיד ונעשית, Ir sheyachid vena'asit, what can I do, Rivka, we
have to get done with the דף. daf. עיר שיחיד ונעשית של
רבים. Ir sheyachid vena'asit shel rabbim. If a city was private and
made public, מערבין את כולה. me'arvin et kullah. Then you could make
an עירוב eruv for the whole city. ושל רבים ונעשית של יחיד,
Ushel rabbim vena'asit shel yachid, if however it was public and made
private, אין מערבין את כולה. ein me'arvin et kullah. You cannot make
an עירוב eruv for the whole city. I'm just going to read
the words and then I'll discuss what this means. אלא אם כן
עושה חוצה לה Ella im ken ose chutzah lah unless you exclude
from the עירוב eruv the city כעיר חדשה שביהודה. ke'ir chadashah shebi'yehudah.
Rashi says that חדשה chadashah here does not mean a new city,
it's actually the name of a city in Yehudah which is called
Chadashah, שיש בה חמשים דיורים דברי רבי יהודה, sheyesh bah chamishim diyarim
divrei Rabbi Yehudah, which has 50 inhabitants. So you have to leave
off 50 inhabitants, you cannot include them in the עירוב. eruv. עירוב
Eruv here does not mean the, you know, the, the posts with
the, with the string over it, it means combining in the loaf
of bread, but effectively it's the same. They would not be able
to carry, 50 people are excluded from that. Because that's what he
says in עיר חדשה ביהודה Ir Chadashah Bi'yehudah was. That's was the
size of that small village. Rabbi Shimon Omer that was the smallest
city. So it's like a, it's like symbolically a city was left,
a, you know, a symbolic city was left off. רבי שמעון אומר
ג' חצרות של שני בתים, Rabbi Shimon Omer gimmel chatzerot shel shenei
batim, it could be much smaller, three courtyards each one of two
houses is enough, symbolizes a city and you leave them off. So
here's this interesting idea, private public city and not in doing the
entire city together. What is the issue of private and public? So
Rashi says, Rashi uses this משנה mishnah to anchor this idea, which
is not in the גמרא gemara and starts in the גאונים, ge'onim,
that you need 600,000 people for there to be a רשות הרבים.
reshut harabbim. And he says public city means there are 600,000, private
means that there are not. And it's interesting though because within the
600,000 there's interesting debates in the פוסקים, Poskim, even if you accept
that leniency, what does 600,000 mean? 600,000 living in the city, 600,000
traveling on the road, traveling on the road daily? So here רש"י
Rashi actually says it means 600,000 living in the city, not actually
using the road. And that's what's defined as... as a רבים. Rabim.
נעשה של יחיד Naaseh shel yachid means that now you don't have
that many inhabitants. And when you have a יחיד, Yachid, a private
one that became public, it means that it was small and now
more people are living in there, or, and this is interesting, רש"י
Rashi says another way it means that it became public is not
that now you have
600,000 city inhabitants, but that 600,000 people come in, like on market
days. So it was became a market city. Now again, the reason
I'm mentioning that is within this idea of 600,000, this becomes an
important question. What does it
mean? Using the... that use the רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim daily? That's
normally how we explain it in order to solve a lot of
עירוב Eruv problems and say, oh, even Manhattan doesn't have 600,000 people
that use any particular street on a daily basis. Or does it
mean living in the city? Or according to one position, what רש"י
Rashi says here, it even means 600,000 that come into the
city, even if they don't live in the city. So that's how
רש"י Rashi explained it. So how does רש"י Rashi explain the משנה?
Mishnah? If you had a city that had 600,000 people, it was
a public city, which means it potentially could have a רשות הרבים,
Reshus Harabim, a biblical רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. It doesn't actually. You
don't have a major street that goes from the one end to
the other that's 16 אמות Amos wide, but at least it has
the potential of having a רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. So that's more
problematic. And then it became private. So since it's now private, we
allow you to do the entire city as one and we don't
have this interesting idea of leaving over a section. I'm sorry, did
I do it the wrong? I did the reverse, right. That actually
would have made more sense, that's the problem. Okay. If it started
private and now it's public, right, since it doesn't actually have a
רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim but just in theory could have a רשות
הרבים, Reshus Harabim, this is the way רש"י Rashi says, and it
also started as private, we allow you to do the whole one
big עירוב. Eruv. It's very counter-intuitive. Because now it's public and now
it should be more problematic. But if somehow it started as public
and now it's private... So it was a public and had a
רשות הרבים? Reshus Harabim? He doesn't say. But in order that you
somehow won't confuse that with the city that starts public and remains
public, therefore we have to do this little thing to be היכר
Heker so you don't accidentally come and make an עירוב Eruv around
a רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. So it's very strange obviously. It's very
strange that the idea is that the way the city started... You
can sort of understand that, some cities, people remember their heyday and
they don't sort of relate to their current status. So somehow if
it started as a huge city, people still think of it that
way even if now it's private, so you leave a little section
over so you don't accidentally come to make an עירוב Eruv around
an actual רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. Whereas if it started private and
now it's big and public, we assume you'll remember and you don't
have to worry so much. That's the way רש"י Rashi explains, although
it is strange why public now public should be a bigger issue.
The רמב"ן Ramban says differently. The רמב"ן Ramban says, he reads the
משנה Mishnah much more simply. The רמבמ"ן Ramban is very skeptical of
this idea of 600,000 being a requirement. And he says public and
private means exactly what it means, exactly what it sounds like it
means. It means ownership. So if you had a private city, literally
one person owned it, okay, and then it became public, then people
came in and moved in and bought land. That's one scenario. And
the other is, it was public and now it became private. And
according to the רמב"ן, Ramban, one of the criteria for having a
biblical רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim is that it actually is a publicly
owned road. If it's privately owned, even if it's a major thoroughfare,
it cannot be a רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. For him ownership matters.
So he therefore says, if it started off as private and now
it's public, we're a little bit more lenient, and he himself asks
the question, he says why? Now it's public, now it should be
more problematic. So he says, well, maybe public doesn't really mean public.
Maybe it means that they're all renting it but I still own
it all. Or maybe it means that I sold the houses but
I still own the streets. So now we have like Jackie Robinson
highway. So he says, literally Jackie Robinson, I own the street. So
anyway, that's how he explains, everybody struggles with why are we more
lenient if now it's public? That should be more problematic. So but
nevertheless, the basic difference is that רש"י Rashi says it's about having
600,000 people, that gives it the potential of being a רשות הרבים,
Reshus Harabim, and the רמב"ן Ramban says it's about being owned by
the public as opposed to owned by a private individual. Owned by
the public is what gives it a potential of being רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabim. But both of them struggle with why are we more
lenient when it used to be private and now it's public as
opposed to the reverse? Like logically it should have been the opposite.
We should have gone by the here and now. So the רמב"ן's
Ramban answer is that when we say now it's public it doesn't
literally mean public. It means that people are renting or whatever but
I still own it all, but the street and the major thoroughfare.
but the street and the major thoroughfares are still owned by private
individual. Yes, Charlie.
This רמב״ן Ramban's opinion actually matters in a few places in Baltimore
and
Honolulu; most of the land is not owned by the people who
live there, there's ground rent.
Okay, interesting. And the highways too? Are roads...
The highways are public.
In general, right.
The streets, the homes, the land.
Interesting, right, interesting. Okay, so let's see the גמרא. Gemara. So the
גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי יחיד ונעשה רבים? heichi dami yachid vena'aseh
rabbim? What is the scenario? And the way the רמב״ן Ramban reads
this question is: Why are we lenient if now it's public? So
the גמרא Gemara is particularly looking for a scenario that would explain
why we could be lenient
if
now it's a public
city. So אמר רב יהודה כגון דאיסקורתא דריש גלותא, Amar Rav Yehuda
kegon de'iskurta de'resh galuta, like the city of Iskurta of the ריש
גלותא Resh Galuta that presumably used to be owned by him privately
and now it's
public. So אמר ליה רב נחמן מאי טעמא? Amar leih Rav Nachman
mai ta'ama? Why are you giving it this particular status of being
public or using this as a particular example? אי נימא משום דשכיחי
גבי הרמנא מתרמי אהדדי Ei neima mishum deshchichi gabei harmana mitrami ahadadi
because people are all going there because that's where, like, you know,
the ruler is, or maybe it also means specifically that they are
going to get like special license from him because we know the
ריש גלותא Resh Galuta gave people license to, like, you know, be
on a בית דין Beit Din and so on. And therefore, since
there's a lot of people around and they're all maybe in the
same location, they're all by the ריש גלותא, Resh Galuta, they'll remind
one another not to carry. So כולי ישראל נמי, Kullei Yisrael nami,
so in any city where there are Jews, ובשבתא דריגלא שכיחי גבי
הדדי, U'beshabta de'rigla shchichi gabei hadadi, they all get together שבת Shabbos
morning. Now why do they all get together on שבת Shabbos morning?
To daven. Look at רש״י. Rashi. רש״י Rashi says דשבתא שכיחי אהדדי,
Deshabta shchichi ahadadi, it's the fifth wide line, לשמוע דרשה. lishmo'a drasha.
So that's very interesting. So he assumes that maybe they have, you
know, smaller, they get together like in smaller שולן shuls for the
davening, but since that they all get together, that's to give a
דרשה. drasha. There's maybe one major רב Rav and he gave the
דרשה drasha for the whole city, right? So it's quite interesting. רש״י
Rashi says that the major gathering together is for the דרשה, drasha,
not for davening. But what's going on here? Get together, remind one
another. So again, the רמב״ן, Ramban, I'll read it the way the
רמב״ן Ramban reads it. He reads it that this is the question:
Why are we lenient? Now it's a רבים, rabbim, right? Why should
we be so lenient? So says no, no, no, because what we
mean by רבים rabbim is we don't literally mean that it's owned
by the רבים, rabbim, or whatever, we mean that it's by the,
it means that a lot of people gather there. Maybe it's still
owned by an individual. Or, even if it's owned by the רבים,
rabbim, if they're all gathering together, then we can assume they'll remind
one another, "Oh yes, you know, we're now a רבים," rabbim, it'll
remind us all that we're a רבים rabbim and we won't come
to carry because we're all around there. So then if that's true,
even a city that was always של רבים shel rabbim we should
be lenient, which is what the גמרא Gemara says, because we always
get together on שבת Shabbos and we'll remind one another. So according
to the רמב״ן, Ramban, the question is: Why are we being lenient
if even if it used to be יחיד, yachid, if now it's
רבים? rabbim? And the גמרא Gemara's trying to answer that by saying
maybe we'll remind one another. But then the גמרא Gemara's like, "Well
then, if it's, then..." Well that's the גמרא Gemara's response back, then
we should always be lenient. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara's
answer is. So it says, אלא אמר רב נחמן כגון דאיסקורתא דנתזואי.
Ella amar Rav Nachman kegon de'iskarta de'nat'zu'ei.
It's like this particular city of this guy called נתזואי Natzu'ei which
is a private individual. So the רמב״ן Ramban says again, trying to
make sense of this, that what that means is they knew that
this was a particular private city, and even after it became public,
it wasn't fully public. That he rented the land, but he actually
continued owning it, or as I said before, he owned the major
thoroughfares, that remained private. So that according to the רמב״ן, Ramban, the
גמרא Gemara is basically asking the question anybody asks on this משנה:
Mishna: Why are we more lenient if now it's public? Who cares
about what it used to be in the past? And his answer
is: it's not fully public now. Okay? Which is not פשט pshat
of the משנה, Mishna, but at least the רמב״ן Ramban wants to
bring that problem into the discussion of the גמרא. Gemara. Yes. I
had
thought that שבת דרשות Shabbat drashos were a 19th-century...
No, actually not. Not at all. No, no, no. Scholars believe, you
know, that the a lot of like the stuff you find in
מדרש רבה, Midrash Rabbah, the openings of מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah were
often, you know, דרשות, drashos, and the like the שאילתות She'iltos which
basically starts with a question, then does a whole little דרשה drasha
then introduces הלכה, halacha, then comes back and answers the question with
a classic sort of ancient form of a דרשה. drasha. So yes,
the assumption is actually that the דרשות drashos might have been one
of the like earliest, you know, reasons that basically people gathered together,
exactly what רש״י Rashi says, you know, and that one of, you
know, it's a very early form. Yes. It says it before רגל,
regel, it says
it... Well, that's right. The שבתא דריגלא, Shabta de'rigla, I mean that's
כלה, Kalla, right?
That was in the afternoon.
Yes, yeah, yeah, but this was on a weekly שבת Shabbos basis
and the assumption is that that is שבתא. shabta. Right.
So what's our answer, what's our answer
the גמרא Gemara is saying it's so... So according to the רמב״ן,
Ramban, the answer, according to רש״י Rashi it's just an illustration of
a case of private becoming public and it's not clear what the
problem and what the answer is. According to the רמב״ן, Ramban, the
question is, why are we being so
lenient?
Yeah, because
then at least we will confuse it with a case that was
that was a case was genuinely רבים. rabbim. I know, it's like
חסורי מחסרא chasuri mechasra בסיפא. binseifa. It's not really good a good
a clear why we're you know why we're more lenient in the
first case and the second. It should be the opposite. Okay, תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: עיר של יחיד ונעשית של רבים. Ir shel yachid
venaaseis shel rabbim. Now we're going to look at this. Okay, according
to the משנה, Mishna, the only difference between public versus private, starting
one way and going the other, is do we force you to
leave over a section so you remember the problems of רשות הרבים?
reshus harabbim? Now we talk about the actual act of making a
you know an עירוב eruv and making and allowing you to carry
in the whole city. עיר של יחיד ונעשית של רבים, Ir shel
yachid venaaseis shel rabbim, it was the case of the משנה Mishna
which is the better case. It started private and is now public.
רשות הרבים עוברת בתוכה, Reshus harabbim overes besochah, and you have a
real רשות הרבים reshus harabbim in it. So now you should have
a real major problem. כיצד מערבין אותה, Keitzad mearvin osah, how do
you make an עירוב eruv in it? עושה לחי מכאן ולחי מכאן
או קורה מכאן וקורה מכאן. Oseh lechi mikan ulechi mikan o korah
mikan vekorah mikan. So you make either a לחי lechi or a
קורה korah on the two ends of the opening and and closing
of you know of the two the front and the back of
the street, like imagine the street goes straight through the city. ונושא
ונותן באמצע, Venoise u’nosein be’emtza, and you can carry in the middle.
Now I should by the way mention an interesting thing in terms
of the language and the verb use here because I keep on
telling you that the word עירוב eruv always means the joining together
in the loaf of bread, it does not mean putting up the
structure. That's called like a מחיצה mechitzah or צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach.
But here it says how do you make an עירוב eruv and
it tells you how you make the structure so that you can
carry. So the use of עירוב eruv coming to mean the actual
structure that surrounds that you can carry, not the actual loaf of
bread. Now what it probably means is what allows you to come
together in the loaf of bread after you've made this structure. But
you see how those become you know that word starts to evolve
in meaning where it comes to mean the actual making of that
structure.
So it's the same מחלוקת machlokes we have with חנניה. Chananya.
Yeah, we're going to see this. Okay, because this is pretty crazy.
This sounds like you can make an עירוב eruv around רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim. So so hold off because the גמרא Gemara is going
to say it's only the opinion of
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. ואין מערבין אותה לחצאין. Ve’ein me’arvin osah lachatza’in.
You cannot do half the city. אלא או כולה, Ella o kullah,
either you do the whole city as an
עירוב eruv together, או מבוי מבוי בפני עצמו, O mavoi mavoi bifnei
atzmo, or every individual street. We'll see what that means in a
minute. היתה של רבים ברישא רבים, Haisa shel rabbim be-reisha rabbim, if
it began as a public city and remains a public city, ואין
לה אלא פתח אחד, Ve’ein lah ella pesach echad, but it's not
a street that goes straight through from one opening to the other.
It's a dead end street. Okay, it only has one outlet. So
that's not a real רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So therefore מערבין את
כולה, mearvin es kullah, you can do an עירוב eruv around all
of it. So before we we analyze this, what I should mention
is that this ברייתא Beraisa makes it clear that the idea of
whether it was public or private not only has implications for do
I have to leave a part of the city off that I'm
not making an עירוב eruv around? Right, because here the difference is
that if it was private, it started private, well let me make
an עירוב eruv even though it's a real רשות הרבים reshus harabbim
goes straight through. Where if it's started public and remains public, we're
going to be more strict, not only on leaving a section off,
but we won't let me make an עירוב eruv around a real
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, only if one end is closed off. Okay,
is that clear? So here it's introduced the idea that the idea
of starting private or starting public has implications for whether you'll let
me make an עירוב eruv around an actual רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
So let's first focus on that, whether you can actually make an
עירוב eruv around a real רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So the גמרא
Gemara starts by saying like
this: מאן תנא דמערב רשות הרבים, Man tanna demeariv reshus harabbim, what
who is the תנא Tanna that says you can make an עירוב
eruv around רשות הרבים? reshus harabbim? So אמר רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei d’Rav Yehoshua, said רב הונא Rav Huna
the son of רב יהושע, Rav Yehoshua, רבי יהודה היא, Rabbi Yehuda
hi, it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, Detanya, as the ברייתא Beraisa
taught. יתר על כן אמר רבי יהודה, Yeseir al kein amar Rabbi
Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said even more than whatever he had
said before. מי שיש לו שני בתים משני צידי רשות הרבים, Mi
sheyesh lo shenei batim mishenei tziddei reshus harabbim, you have two houses
on the two sides of
a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. עושה לחי מכאן ולחי מכאן, Oseh lechi
mikan ulechi mikan, you put a לחי lechi on either side, right,
so you have a...
right? Here's your רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, you have a house here
and a house here, so you make a לחי lechi here and
a לחי lechi here, or קורה korah here and a קורה korah
here, one or the
other. לחי מכאן ולחי מכאן או קורה מכאן וקורה מכאן. ונושא ונותן
באמצע. lechi mikan ulechi mikan o korah mikan vekorah mikan venoise u’nosein
be’emtza, And then you can go ahead and carry in the middle.
אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him, אין מערבין רשות
הרבים בכך, Ein me’arvin reshus harabbim bekach, I'm sorry, that does not
allow that you cannot make an עירוב eruv around רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim with that. Again, notice מערבין me’arvin used for making the structure
around the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, or at least as a stage
in getting to the עירוב. eruv. Okay, so by the way, it
makes sense that it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because besides it's the
exact same language of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, right, the ברייתא Beraisa
said
לחי מכאן ולחי מכאן או קורה מכאן וקורה מכאן Lechi mikan ulechi
mikan o korah mikan vekorah mikan. ונושא ונותן באמצע, Venoise u’nosein be’emtza.
even the ונושא ונותן באמצע. venoise u’nosein be’emtza. So point number one
is this ברייתא Beraisa assumes in theory you can make an עירוב
eruv around a real רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Okay, and it therefore
says, but if it started as רבים rabbim and it's now רבים,
rabbim, so it's the whole city was always רבים, rabbim, we won't
let you do it. One of the ends has to be dead-end.
But if it started as private, we'll let you actually make an
עירוב eruv around רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Now we don't פוסקין posken
that way. The reason it's so important for all the ראשונים Rishonim
who say the idea of six
600,000 makes it
של יחיד, shelyachid,
meaning because that way almost every city becomes של יחיד shelyachid because
if you put that criteria of 600,000, because they basically hold you
can't make an עירוב eruv around a real רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
So therefore it's really important to say that we don't ever have
a real רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Okay, but this ברייתא braisa assumes
not like we פוסקן pasken that you can't make an עירוב eruv
around רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and therefore it only makes a distinction
between whether it started של יחיד shel yachid or it started של
רבים. shel rabbim. So that's the first part of the ברייתא. braisa.
If it started של יחיד shel yachid then you can make an
עירוב eruv around the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim assuming like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda.
Wait, didn't we have a whole debate, you know, with בית שמאי
Beis Shammai you'd need a
צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach, what happens to all that? Okay, this is
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, okay, it's clear from the language, it's רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, we don't פוסקן pasken this way. אמר רב,
Amar Rav, now we move on. So point number one is even
if it's got a real רשות הרבים reshus harabbim maybe you can
make an עירוב eruv in it according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and it says you're allowed to as long as it started off
של יחיד. shel yachid. Now the next part is ואין מערבין אותה
לחצאין, ve'ein me'arvin osah lachatza'in, you cannot do it halfway. Okay, now
why can't you do it halfway? You can always do part of
a city. Why here can you not? So רש״י Rashi basically says,
we'll see the scenarios in a minute, but רש״י Rashi says conceptually
the reason you can't do it partway is because it all used
to be, well the רמב״ן Ramban particularly adds, it all used to
be private. So therefore conceptually it always used to be seen of
as one domain, one property, right? And therefore if you do half
of it then the sense is is that like people there's a
natural sense that you can carry from one to the other, that
this all, because it all used to be one person's domain. So
if you carry in one part, you can carry in the other
part. We didn't think about it as a lot of different people
and maybe, you know, this section can have an עירוב eruv and
this section cannot. So that's why it's more problematic here than in
a normal city to just make an עירוב eruv on part of
it. So what's the scenario where you can't make an עירוב eruv
on part of it? Let's take a look. אמר רב פפא לא
אמרו אלא לאורכה, Amar Rav Pappa lo amru ella le'orkah, that's only
the length, אבל לרחבה מערבין, aval lerachvah me'arvin, but the width you
can. What's the case? The case
is, here, here's your street that goes through your major city, right?
Here's your city, like the Cardo or whatever, right? So and you
have all these courtyards here etc. you have these courtyards here. So
he says when you can't do it halfway, that means that you
can't do like this section by itself and that section by itself.
Why? Because since there's the road that cuts through half of it,
okay some say it even means you can't do it halfway in
the middle of the road, which that would be even much more
obvious. Reason you can't do it halfway in the middle of the
road is how you split, I mean use half of the road
right and you know I can't be that I can use half
the road and not the other half. The fact that I can't,
you know, it's all one and therefore they're competing. But even theoretically
maybe it means I can't use my side, you can't use your
side because the reality is we're both going to want to get
access to the road. We both use that road and that effectively
makes that seen as competing territory. So if we don't, if we
do that, if we do it separately and therefore I can carry
in my domain, I can't carry in yours and vice versa and
we're both competing of the road, that's problematic. Now again, it really
shouldn't be, I mean just straight down the middle of the road
and maybe it is, but it really shouldn't be problematic except that
it started של יחיד. shel yachid. And because it started של יחיד
shel yachid there's going to be an assumption that it's all one.
Because of that assumption that it's all one, it all was conceived
of as all being brought together, therefore if you do it that
way they're competing on the road.
But, he keeps on going, אבל לרחבה מערבין.
aval lerachvah me'arvin.
If you do it this way you can. Why? Because we're not
competing on the road. In theory we can use this part of
the road and we can go out of the city this way.
You can use that part of the road and go out that
way, right, unless you need to go, you
know, the other way.
Okay, I understand, but it's seen as less competition than when we
have the exact same road serving the exact same purpose for both
of us, right? Because then this road is doing the exact same
for both of us and there's no way we're going to split
it down, you know, the middle of it. So אבל לרחבה מערבין.
aval lerachvah me'arvin.
So כמאן Keman says the גמרא, Gemara, דלא כרבי עקיבא, delo ke-Rabbi
Akiva, not like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, דאי כרבי עקיבא de'i ke-Rabbi
Akiva because if it were like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, הא אמר
ha amar he says in another case, רגל המותרת במקומה אוסרת אפילו
שלא במקומה. regel hamutteres bimkomah oseres afilu shelo bimkomah. So what's the
case of רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? The case is that you have
a, you've got a courtyard here, courtyard, you know, one courtyard opening
into the other and this courtyard opens into the public domain. Okay,
so whatever. All right, so this is your רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
this is courtyard A, this is courtyard B. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says let's say B makes a separate עירוב eruv and A
makes a separate עירוב. eruv. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says B
can carry, A cannot carry. Why can A not carry? Because even
though B is מותרת במקומה, mutteres bimkomah, it's muttar for B in
place B, but since the way they get to the street is
through A, it's considered like they are
present. A in A's space, A has B present and doesn't have
an עירוב Eiruv with B, has B, you know, virtually present and
doesn't have an עירוב. Eiruv. So B is מותרת במקומה, moteret bimkomah,
it's muter in its place, but אוסרת שלא במקומה, oseret shelo bimkomah,
it makes gives A a headache because it because it effectively is
in A. So the גמרא Gemara says why isn't this the same,
right? Here we'll call this, you know, B and this A. So
even if A is okay, why doesn't it create problems for B?
Because the answer is obvious because I just told you what's the
answer. Why here does A not create problems for B?
Because A's going a different way.
Because A is able to go a different way. Here the only
reason or, you know, or B, here the only reason is B
is because B's the only way out is through A.
So A has to make an עירוב Eiruv with B in order
for A to carry.
Yes, that scenario. So the גמרא Gemara says, so ah you see
it's not רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. No, the גמרא Gemara says אפילו
תימא רבי עקיבא, afillu teima Rabbi Akiva, it could be רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. עד כאן קאמר רבי עקיבא התם אלא בשתי חצרות זו
לפנים מזו. ad kan ka'amar Rabbi Akiva hatam ella bishtei chatzerot zu
lifnim mizu. That's only two courtyards one interior to the other. דפנימית
לית ליה פתחא אחרינא, dipnimit leit lei pitcha achrina, the inner one
has no other doorway, so they're always going to have to go,
B's going to have to go into A, and therefore it's a
problem. אבל הכא, aval hacha, but here, הני נפקי בהאי פתחא והני
נפקי בהאי פתחא. hani nafki be'hai pitcha vehani nafki be'hai pitcha. A
goes through the northern, you know, exit and B goes through the
southern exit. So they're able to make a separate עירוב. Eiruv. איכא
דאמרי, ika de'amrei, some say, אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, לא
תימא לאורכא הוא דלא מערבין, lo teima le'orka hu de'lo me'arvin, that
he's more strict as this version. Not only can they not make
it lengthwise where they're obviously competing for the road, אבל לרווחא מערבין,
aval lerovcha me'arvin, and you would think that they could make it
widthwise, אלא אפילו לרווחא נמי לא מערבין, ella afillu lerovcha nami lo
me'arvin, they can't even do it widthwise. Okay. Now the גמרא's Gemara
going to say now, כמאן, keman, who's that going like? כרבי עקיבא?
ke'Rabbi Akiva? Is that like רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Because רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva said B creates problems for A. So maybe if you
say you can't do it widthwise, they'll say because you know even
though in theory A could go down and B could go up,
but there's a likelihood that they'll come into one another's zone. So
what's the logic of not doing it widthwise? Is it something based
on רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? The גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו תימא
רבנן, afillu teima Rabbanan, even the רבנן Rabbanan who argue with רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. עד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם, ad kan lo
ka'amrei Rabbanan hatam,
why do the רבנן Rabbanan say that the B and A case
is not a problem in the one courtyard inside the other one?
אלא בשתי חצרות זו לפנים מזו, ella bishtei chatzerot zu lifnim mizu,
two courtyards one inside the other, דפנימית אחדי לדשא ומשתמשה dipnimit achdi
ledasha umishtamsha
because the inner courtyard can in theory close its door. Meaning, the
רבנן Rabbanan say like this according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. They
say look, B is never going to be able to carry in
A. So the fact that B could go or often goes through
A or whatever, that's just creating צרות. tzaros. Nobody is benefiting from
viewing B's travel through A. So for שבת, Shabbat, we'll view it
as if they closed the door. There actually is an opening from
one to the other. Nobody benefits, you know, from going through A.
So therefore effectively they've closed the door and therefore that allows us
to separate them off. So the basic answer is there's a doorway
here, so even the rabbis that say it's not a problem, it's
because they say we can view it as if the doorway is
shut and they're not going to be going through. So how does
that contrast to our case? אבל הכא מי מצית מסלקת
רשות הרבים מהכא. aval hacha mi matzit mesalekat reshus harabbim mehacha. Here,
who can remove the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim from here? So what
does that
mean? So what it basically means is here there's no doorway to
shut. Okay? Here's just a straight road. There's an imaginary line and
it's a straight road and there's no doorway to shut. So here
the reality is even in theory, you know, A could go down
and B could go up, there's no way you could seal the
street off in the middle and in practice they'll be going into
one another's domain. And therefore this is more problematic, so you cannot
do it halfway. Now again, we normally don't say this. Normally we
say a section of the city can be its own עירוב, Eiruv,
another section can do its own עירוב, Eiruv, it's fine. Here the
problem seems to be since it was owned by a יחיד, yachid,
we view it more as everybody sort of getting into everybody else's
space. And because you know we view it as more unified and
that actually creates more of a problem. So therefore you have to
do it all together and because here you could go in the,
you're likely you'll go in the other part of the street, it's
a problem. And there by the courtyards we say there's a way
to prevent you from going. I should mention by the way that
תוספות Tosafot says it is not just the traveling into somebody else's
space that creates the problem. It's the fact that you will come
to actually carry in the other space and use the other space
that's a problem. It's not when we say we close the door,
it doesn't mean that they're trapped in here, you know, effectively. But
okay, anyway that is the issue that here because it's all one
city and because we're dealing with a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, it
creates problems and you have to do it all together. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. This is all according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can do that.
This is all according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, right? I mean
it would be true for the רבנן Rabbanan as well if it
was if it was closed, the... street was, it wasn't a real
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, presumably it would also be true. Okay. אמר
מר Amar mar או כולה או מבוי מבוי בפני עצמה. o kula
o maboi maboi bifnei atzma. Now, you can also do, you don't
have to do the whole city, you can do each מבוי maboi
by itself. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא דלחצרות דלא דאסרי
אהדדי. mai shna delachatzeros delo de'osri ahaddadi. One minute, half and half
you didn't like because they make one another forbidden because they're competing
for the street. מבוי נמי אסרי אהדדי. Maboi nami osri ahaddadi. So
by a מבוי maboi also, you know, the מבוי's maboi open up,
the מבוי's, maboi sorry, not a courtyard, the alleyways, the alleyways open
up into common space. Why should you be able to make individual
alleyways? Classically what would happen there is that here would be your
מבוי, maboi, your מבוי maboi would be your alleyway, here's your houses,
right, and your חצרות chatzeros open up into the
alleyway. Your courts open up into the
street. Okay, so each one can make, every every מבוי maboi can
make its own. But yeah, the מבויים maboyim open up into like
more major
streets. So why does that make it any better? So isn't that
exactly the same problem? So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן
כגון דעבד דקה. hacha bamai askinan kegon de'avad daka. What are we
talking about? You made a little barrier. דאמר רב אידי בר אבין
אמר רב חסדא אחד מבני מבוי שעשה דקה לפתחו אינו אוסר בני
מבוי. de'amar Rav Idi bar Avin amar Rav Chisda echad mibnei maboi
she'asa daka lepitcho eino oser bnei maboi. So, if you have a
דקה, daka, means instead of just doing like a little לחי lechi
or קורה, korah, you actually made a little barrier. Not עשרה טפחים,
asara tefachim, ארבעה טפחים, arba'a tefachim, but you actually made a little
barrier and that effectively seals you off from everything else. Now,
here's the analogy is instructive. The analogy is if you have here
your מבוי maboi and you have your courtyards, right? Now, what happens
if one house doesn't want to participate in the עירוב? eruv? Anybody
know? It makes problems for everybody because you remain your independent space.
Similarly, if one of the חצרות chatzeros doesn't want to participate, it
makes competing space in the alleyway. But, if you make a little
barrier, not just a לחי lechi or קורה, korah, you basically have
signaled I'm not here, I'm not part of this alleyway. The actual
fact that it's an actual barrier. So if you make a little
barrier, then it's not considered yours and all of these guys can
join together. You're fine. So similarly here, it's like I don't get
it. If you're viewing this because, and again, it's important to emphasize
what רש"י Rashi says, because it was all owned by a יחיד,
yachid, you're viewing it all as shared space by definition and therefore
it all has to be together. So even individual מבויים maboyim should
be competing for the main street because it's all sort of being
pulled together. So basically says the מבוי maboi to the main street
is like the חצר chatzer to the מבוי. maboi. And the same
way the חצר chatzer to the מבוי, maboi, a little barrier cuts
it off and removes it from being a problem, the מבויים maboyim
to the main street, a little barrier cuts it off and allows
that to not be a problem and allows them to not be
competing on the main street. Okay, so that's the idea here. But
again, specifically, normally none of this is an issue. This is specifically
because it used to be של יחיד. shel yachid.
And that's why they're able to go there.
What? And that's why each person, you can't use that you can't
carry in that street, but every every מבוי maboi can make its
individual עירוב. eruv. Now normally it's never a problem. Normally, of course,
that's exactly what you do. Every מבוי maboi makes its individual עירוב.
eruv. But here, it seemed because it used because it is it
was של יחיד, shel yachid, it's as if they are being forced
together and they're all present in the same thoroughfare. And therefore they're
competing. Okay, so therefore you need to do an additional thing. You
either have to get them all in together in the עירוב, eruv,
or you have to do something in order to designate that they're
not going to be competing in the main thoroughfare.
Yes, that's such an interesting situation
because many cities, for example the Bronx, it's the Bronxes because it
used to belong to Mr. Bronx.
Really? I didn't know that. Okay.
Well, the Bronx was never an independent city. It's always been part
of, all right, but whatever.
I mean, we're not talking about politically. But no, I mean, so
that's, look, it's a good question. I think that basically להלכה, lehalacha,
because those that adopt the 600,000 criteria, you know, read this רש"י's
Rashi way, so יחיד yachid and רבים, rabbim, was there 600,000 was
there not, and since effectively we try to say there's never real
600,000
somehow, it makes a lot of this moot. But you are right
in theory
this would be relevant because in that case that it used to
be של יחיד, shel yachid, right now we're seeing the way רש"י
Rashi reads the גמרא, Gemara, that that actually creates problems, doesn't solve
problems.
And it wasn't a city back then.
It was a private property. Right. So that's true. You mean it
never had like multiple people living on it. He just sold all
the land and then it became, right. I'm sure there were places
that were private and you're right, because here you are seeing when
we make עירוב's eruv we don't make it on the entire city.
So it's a good point like
where the... Right, but we don't want to admit that any city
nowadays has 600,000, so that's part of the issue. But no, Don
makes an excellent point because here we're finding out that של יחיד
shel yachid actually is more of a חומרא chumra according to at
least the way רש״י Rashi understands this גמרא, Gemara, yeah.
And the original Manhattan neighborhood from the 1960s actually covered the entire
island.
Ah, right, that's interesting. But most עירובין eruvin nowadays split רשות הרבים
reshus harabim in half. They exactly do that. One after, you know,
now if you're willing to admit it's a real רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, you know, but whatever they do, they split a major thoroughfare
in half. So if you say that it used to be של
יחיד, shel yachid, you've got a problem. It's true, it's a good
question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. We just, two dots. היתה של רבים ונעשית של רבים. Haysah
shel rabim venaasis shel rabim. Continuing on the ברייתא. braisa. Or no,
actually, just going back to the משנה. Mishnah. The ברייתא braisa then
said if it was all רבים, rabim, then it's going to be
harder to make an עירוב eruv and then it's only if one
of the streets is a dead-end street. So that's certainly that the
basic idea that even according to רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, according to
the way we've read the ברייתא, braisa, that you could make an
עירוב eruv on a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, even that was limited
to the idea that it was once של יחיד. shel yachid. And
clearly we פוסקן pasken you can't make an
עירוב eruv around a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, a real רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim. But now going to the משנה Mishnah that's about this
idea of leaving over space, that if it once was, if it
began as רבים, rabim, you have to leave over a section that's
not part of the עירוב. eruv. It's actually a little bit ironic,
right? If it starts as a יחיד, yachid, you have to make
the עירוב eruv on the whole thing. If it starts as a
רבים, rabim, you have to leave over space. So it's actually quite
ironic, you know, but that's somewhat indicating that idea that somehow its
origin gives it an identity. So if it starts as a יחיד,
yachid, you have to make it more uniform and if it starts
as a רבים, rabim, you have to signify that it's a רבים
rabim and you don't make it unified. So now we're moving exactly
to that, that if it started as a רבים, rabim, you leave
over a space.
Even the way the רמב״ם Rambam read it, that it really was
רבים. rabim.
Yeah, and then, and then, you know, it became, in both of
the first cases.
Yeah, he read it that it never fully became, it was always
really privately owned but now like just more רבים rabim were using
it.
Yeah, that's the way the רמב״ם Rambam reads it. Okay, so רבי
זירא, Rebbi Zeira, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, but
that's just to get the basic idea again, to repeat it, that
if it began as a יחיד, yachid, that more unifies it and
you have to make a singular עירוב eruv or make these little
bit barriers to allow sections to divide off. And if it began
as a רבים, rabim, then you have to emphasize that by leaving
a section not included. Okay, רבי זירא ערב למתא דבי רבי חייא.
Rebbi Zeira areiv lemasa devei Rebbi Chiya. ולא שביק לשיור. Velo shavik
leshiur. So רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira made an עירוב eruv around the
city of רבי חייא, Rebbi Chiya, the village, and didn't leave over
any part of it. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי
Abaye said to him, מאי טעמא עביד מר הכי? Mai taama avid
mar hachi? Why did you do that? Presumably he thought that it
had begun to be של רבים shel rabim and therefore you needed
to leave something over. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him,
סבי דההיא מתא אמרו לי Sabei de'hahi masa amru li because the
elders of that city told me דרב חייא בר אשי מערב כולה.
de'Rav Chiya bar Ashi me'areiv kullah. That Rav Chiya bar Ashi used
to make an עירוב eruv of the whole city. So I figured,
why is that? Why didn't he leave a part over? ואמינא, Va'amina,
so I said, שמע מינה, shema mina, from this I can infer,
עיר של יחיד ונעשית של רבים היא. Ir shel yachid venaasis shel
rabim hi. It was a city that once was private because I
heard that Rav Chiya used to not make it on the whole
city—the only way you can make it on the whole city is
if it started off as being private. He did make a city.
Yes, right. Rav Chiya made it on the whole city, and the
only way you could do that is if it started being private.
So I did the same, I made it on the whole city.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, לא, לדידי
אמרו לי הנהו סבי, Lo, lidi'di amru li hanhu sabei, these elders
told me, האי אשפה הוה ליה מחד גיסא. Hai ashpa hava lei
michad gisa.
And that the reason they were able to, they made it on
the whole thing was because it never had a real רשות הרבים,
reshus harabim, that the major street used to end in a garbage
dump and therefore they were able to make it on the whole
city. והשתא דאפנייה לאשפה, Vahashta de'afneiyeh le'ashpa, now that the garbage dump
has been removed, הויא ליה כשני פתחים ואסיר. Havei lei kishnei pesachim
va'asir.
It's like, like we had before, you know, it's got, it's got
two ends, two openings, and it's a real רשות הרבים reshus harabim
and now it's a problem. אמר ליה לאו אדעתאי. Amar lei lav
ada'atai. Oh, I wasn't thinking about it, it's a good point. Okay,
so what becomes interesting here is is that the idea that you
have to leave a portion over is only when there's not a
real—only when there's a real רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. When there's not
a real רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, right, you don't need to leave
a portion over. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
right, for the answer was, was that it may have always been
של רבים shel rabim but wasn't a problem if it ended in
a garbage dump. So בעי מיניה רב אמי בר אדא הרפנאה מרבה.
Ba'ei minei Rav Ami bar Adda Harpana'ah me'Rabbah. So whatever, Rav Ami
asked from Rabbah, סולא מכאן ופתח מכאן
מהו? Sula mikan ufesach mikan mahu?
Since we just said that the only time that it's a problem
of a real רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, getting very messy, the only
time it's a problem of a real רשות הרבים reshus harabim whether
to make an עירוב eruv around it or whether to the idea
that you have to... And you have to leave a section of
the city undone is if it's got openings at both ends. Only
then is it more problematic of making an עירוב, eruv, you know,
and is it an issue about leaving something up, leaving a part
of the city left off if it's שירט של רבים? serat shel
rabbim? So he says what let's say, so give me an example
what that there was a garbage dump and that made it easier
to do the whole thing as a city. Let's say it says
there's a wall here but there also happens to be a ladder
that lets you get over the wall. Okay, is that like it
has two openings and is going to meet make it harder to
do a רשות reshut to do an עירוב eruv of the whole
city?
Sorry, someone in charge of this ladder, is it taken away, is
it always there, who knows?
Okay, סולמא מכאן ופתח מכאן מהו? sulma mikan upetach mikan mahu? אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, הכי אמר רב, hachi
amar Rav, this is what רב Rav says, סולם תורת פתח עליו.
sulam torat petach alav. A סולם sulam
is like an opening and therefore it's a problem, it's like it
has the road has openings at both ends and when it's that
way it's much harder to make an עירוב eruv around it especially
if it's שירט של רבים serat shel rabbim and okay you cannot
make an עירוב eruv around the whole city and maybe not around
the road, even the road itself. אמר להו, amar lehu, אמר להו
רב נחמן, amar lehu Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman says
לא תציתו ליה, lo tetzitu lei, don't listen to him. הכי אמר
רב אדא אמר רב, hachi amar Rav Ada amar Rav, this is
what רב אדא Rav Ada said in the name of רב, Rav,
סולם תורת פתח עליו ותורת מחיצה עליו. sulam torat petach alav vetorat
mechitzah alav. If you have a wall with a ladder you're you
have both leniencies, it both serves as an opening if that's lenient
or as a wall if you need a wall. What does that
mean? תורת מחיצה עליו torat mechitzah alav כדאמרן, kide'amaran, it's a מחיצה
mechitzah for our purposes so the street is considered to be a
dead-end street so that actually makes it easier to make an עירוב
eruv in the whole city because it's considered to be a dead-end
street. And what is תורת פתח עליו? torat petach alav? But it's
also considered to be an opening, what for what purpose? בסולם שבין
שתי חצרות, besulam shebein shtei chatzeirot, if it's between two courtyards, רצו
אחד מערב רצו שנים
מערבין. ratzu echad me'arev ratzu shenayim me'arvin. If they want what's the
story you have two courtyards? If you have two courtyards like we
sort of discussed that before, you have two courtyards like this, let's
say I don't know they both open into רשות הרבים reshut harabim
and there's an opening between them, okay so you have these courtyards
so because
so can they, you know, make separate עירובין eruvin or do they
have to make are they all considered one courtyard? Okay, so if
it's considered to be like totally open one to the other then
they have to make one עירוב, eruv, they're all one. So he
says if you've got however a wall with a ladder, okay then
it's like a פתח, petach, that's the same as a פתח petach
as an opening and an opening allows you to say if we
want we can consider ourselves one because we can and we can
make one עירוב eruv if we want, we don't have to use
the opening and therefore we consider ourselves separate, so the ladder is
as good as an opening meaning a ladder makes it possible to
go to access the other, right, but it doesn't make it necessary.
So here it's actually if you think about it it's very logical.
Here the idea has to be that it's only a problematic רשות
הרבים reshut harabim if this is considered completely open. It's not completely
open, it's a wall with a ladder so that's enough of a
problem that it's not a רשות הרבים reshut harabim so it counts
as a מחיצה. mechitzah. Here can am I allowed to make one
עירוב? eruv? Yes, the ladder makes it possible to access and therefore
you're allowed to make one עירוב eruv so the ladder actually gives
you the best of both, serves as a מחיצה mechitzah when it's
necessary and serves as a פתח petach when it's necessary. So we
will see more of this tomorrow, wow.